{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this region, Vespasian served with the Legio II Augusta and participated in the Battle of the Medway. This province’s northernmost reach came with Agricola’s victory at Mons Graupius over the Caledonians. The Legio IX Hispania supposedly disappeared in this province, where Gaius Suetonius Paulus suppressed an uprising of the Iceni tribe after his victory in the Battle of Watling Street. Hadrian’s Wall lies in, for ten points, what Roman province where Boudica sacked Londonimium?",
      "answer": [
        "Britannia",
        "descriptions of the island of Great Britain"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "According to legend, after Claude Harmon performed this feat, Ben Hogan replied “How was your shot?” On Sunday, April 10th, Shane Lowry, Davis Love III, and Louis Oosthuizen [oost-hoy-zen] all accomplished this feat, with Oosthuizen requiring a bounce off of J.B. Holmes’ ball. This rare feat has occurred 27 times in competition at Augusta National, but is significantly more common on the Wednesday of Masters week, during the Par 3 contest. For ten points, name this feat in which a golfer finishes a hole with a minimum amount of work.",
      "answer": "making a hole-in-one or an ace at the Masters"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first elected King of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth was from this family, as was the first husband of Mary, Queen of Scots. One ruler from this family hosted the Field of the Cloth of Gold. Catherine de Medici’s husband belonged to this family, which originally took power after the extinction of the Capet Dynasty. This family fought against the Plantagents in the Hundred Years War. For ten points, name this French dynasty which was succeeded by the Bourbons and whose members included Francis I.",
      "answer": "House of Valois"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this battle, Lauzun’s Legion was able to repulse a foraging party led by Banastre Tarleton. During this battle, the Gatinois regiment provided carpenters to break down palisades at Redoubt 9. One myth about this battle notes that the general who fired the first cannon shot ended up hitting a dinner table where his enemies were eating. This battle ended with the playing of the tune “The World Turned Upside Down” while Charles O’ Hara surrendered. For ten points, name this 1781 battle in which Cornwallis surrendered to George Washington.",
      "answer": "Battle of Yorktown"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man depicted the murder of a working class family during the July Monarchy in his lithograph Rue Transnonain. One work by this artist shows a photographer in a hot air balloon taking pictures. Another work by this artist satirically depicts an obese Louis-Phillipe being fed humans as the title creature. This artist of Nadar Elevating Photography to the Height of Art and Gargantuan depicted a peasant family in a namesake carriage on a train. For ten points, name this 19th century French artist of Third Class Carriage.",
      "answer": "Honore Daumier"
    },
    {
      "question": "A procession celebrating this substance takes place in Bruges [broozh] on Ascension Day. This substance, which is created in the epiclesis, is addressed in a litany as the “refreshment of souls” and “price of our salvation” that is “flowing forth in the Agony.” Weingarten Abbey contains a sample of this substance collected by Longinus. An act in persona Christi instills this substance in an unchanged species in the act of Transubstantiation. For ten points, name this substance that is represented in the Eucharist by wine.",
      "answer": [
        "blood of Christ or Jesus for “Christ",
        "”",
        "Holy Blood"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Soybean farmers used road blocks to protest this leader’s plans to increase export taxes. Protests against this leader erupted after the murder of prosecutor Alberto Nisman. This leader was widely criticized for tweeting about “lice and petloleum” during a visit to China. This leader succeeded her husband Nestor, who led the Peronist Justicialist Party. For ten points, name this female former President of Argentina that lost a December 2015 election to Mauricio Macri.",
      "answer": "Christina Fernandez de Kirchner"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was investigated by John Kenlon. Kate Alterman was made to repeat her testimony about this event multiple times by Max Steuer, leading the jury to believe that she had memorized what to say during the trial of Max Blanck and Isaac Harris. The ILGWU grew substantially in the aftermath of this event, during which William Gunn Shephard wrote of seeing women jump out of windows because doors had been locked. For ten points, name this 1911 event in which a fire in the Asch building killed 146 garment workers.",
      "answer": "Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "In March 2016, researchers found thousands of artifacts from this man’s ship Esmeralda off the coast of Oman. The Zamorin believed that this man was not a royal ambassador because his gifts contained no gold or silver. He named Natal while passing through on Christmas Day. The Sao Gabriel was the flagship of this explorer, who visited Mombasa and Calicut. For ten points, name this explorer who, under the patronage of Henry the Navigator, became the first European to see India while sailing for Portugal.",
      "answer": "Vasco de Gama"
    },
    {
      "question": "The implementation of this policy was in question in Evenwel v. Abbott. In his decision in Reynolds v. Sims, Chief Justice Warren applied this principle, writing that “legislators represent people, and not acres or trees.” In 2016, the Supreme Court upheld a ruling that convicted felons and children are included in one half of this policy, even though they are ineligible to participate in the other half. The U.S. Senate does not abide by this policy; after each census, districts are re-drawn to allow the House to more accurately abide by it. For ten points, give this four-word phrase for the idea that political power should be equal for all voters.",
      "answer": [
        "One person, one vote",
        "man",
        "woman for person"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Foy and Frederick Heinde were the first two men to be wounded in this event. This event was wrapped up quickly so that Robert Attison would not have an excuse to use state militia. Alexander Berkman and Emma Goldman plotted to assassinate the man they thought responsible for this event, in which a flotilla obstructed a barge’s attempt to travel toward this event. This reaction to the harsh policies of Henry Clay Frick resulted in 12 deaths and the downfall of an ironworkers union. For ten points, name this 1892 strike and lockout at a steelworks in Pittsburgh.",
        "answer": "Homestead Strike"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Homestead Strike was opposed by this detective group, known for their strikebreaking.",
        "answer": "Pinkerton Detective Agency"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This process took place annually in a two-stage system; first the question of whether it would happen that year, then the question of its target. One man helped an illiterate citizen perform this process by writing his own name on a potshard. Someone undergoing this process was guaranteed the return of their property after they endured it for ten years, though the Assembly could recall them early, as was done for Cimon and the father of Pericles. For ten points, name this process of democratically-chosen, temporary exile from Athens, a term that now refers generally to a process of shunning someone.",
        "answer": [
          "ostracism",
          "word forms, like ostracize"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The illiterate voter asked this Athenian to write his name in the 482 BC ostracism vote, because he was “sick of hearing [this man] everywhere called ‘the Just.’”",
        "answer": "Aristides the Just"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In an attempt to turn back liberal reforms, this man adopted the Plan of Cuernavaca, which culminated in this man gaining dictatorial power. Florencio Villarreal plotted the removal of this man, who surrendered one war via the Treaty of Velasco. After this man was wounded in the Pastry War, he gave his leg a full military burial. This man was thwarted at the Battle of San Jacinto by Sam Houston a month after leading troops against a San Antonio mission defended by Davy Crockett. For ten points, name this Mexican general who opposed Texan independence at the Alamo.",
        "answer": "Antonio L´opez de Santa Anna"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This was the 1854 revolutionary plan devised by Florencio Villareal that sought to end Santa Anna’s final dictatorship.",
        "answer": "Plan of Ayutla"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 2013 picture of this man shows him with an inflated throat pouch in a “show of dominance over fellow Congressional males.” A 2016 satirical article included another photoshopped picture of this man covered in blood holding a severed head. That article ostensibly quoted this man as saying “Do not attempt to silence the voice of the American people,” and reported that he had mailed his victim’s hand to Sri Srinivasan as a warning. For ten points, name this politician who, fictionally, killed Merrick Garland in March 2016, “fulfilling” his threat that Republicans would not consider a Supreme Court nominee before the election, a promise he made as Senate Majority Leader.",
        "answer": "Mitch McConnell BONUS:Theaforementionedarticleswerepublishedbywhatsatiricalinternetnewssource,whichstopped producing a print version in 2013? ANSWER: The Onion 5 Thaddeus Stevens quipped that a holder of this position, Simon Cameron, “wouldn’t steal a red hot stove” in defense of the corruption charge that led to his resignation in 1862. Albert Gallatin criticized one holder of this position after a disastrous series of events including the surrender of William Hull. The Confederation Congress appointed Benjamin Lincoln to this position, after which he was succeeded by Henry Knox, who held this position under George Washington. For ten points, name this Cabinet office that was broken up in 1947 ANSWER: Secretary of War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Secretary of War under Franklin Pierce later appointed Judah Benjamin, James Seddon, and three others as his own Secretaries of War.",
        "answer": "Jefferson Finis Davis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s post-World War II years are described in the nihilistic novel The Decay of the Angel. A novel set in this country features characters called The Minister of the Left and the Minister of the Right. Father Rodrigues’ journal provides much of the action in a novel set in this country called Silence. The customs of this country’s court life are detailed in The Pillow Book, as well as a novel featuring Lady Aoi. For ten points, name this country, the setting of The Tale of Genji.",
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pillow Book was written by what Heian-era poet, who served Empress Teishi?",
        "answer": "Sei Shonagon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThePanjshirvalleywascapturedearlyoninthiswar.ThiswarwasprecededbyOperationStorm-333, which replaced Hafizullah Amin with Babrak Karmal. It was prompted by the deterioration of relations with Nur Muhammed Taraki, who had seized power in the Saur Revolution. This conflict was opposed by Operation Cyclone, in which Stinger missiles were given to mujahideen warriors by CIA operatives. For ten points, name this decade-long conflict, a Soviet invasion of a Middle Eastern country.",
        "answer": "Soviet invasion of Afghanistan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Soviet invasion of Afghanistan began under this Soviet Premier, who signed the Helsinki Accords.",
        "answer": "Leonid Brezhnev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While looking at this body of water, Frederick Billings remembered the George Berkeley quote “westward the course of empire takes its way.” Extensive bath works known as the Sutro Baths overlook this body of water. To prevent Confederate warships from passing through this body of water during the Civil War, Fort Point was built at its southern end. This strait, south of Marin Peninsula, is spanned by a structure that was designed by Joseph Strauss and is painted International Orange. For ten points, name this strait that connects the Pacific to San Francisco Bay and is spanned by a namesake bridge.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Gate",
          "Golden Gate Bridge"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the south end of the Golden Gate is what former Spanish military fort founded by Juan Bautista de Anza?",
        "answer": "Presidio of San Francisco"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s attempt to take a settlement on the Penobscot River failed after the Captain of the Good Hope prematurely started a bombardment. Thomas Morton labeled this man “Captain Shrimp” after the latter removed him from Mount Wollaston. This man failed to capture Corbitant in a raid on Nemasket, although the raid influenced Corbitant to declare his loyalty to King James. For ten points, name this soldier, the chief defender of the Plymouth Colony and the subject of a Longfellow poem about his Courtship.",
        "answer": "Myles Standish"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Myles Standish frequently advised what first governor of the Plymouth Colony?",
        "answer": "William Bradford"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FEMINISM",
      "prompt": "In the history of feminism, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1920 Constitutional Amendment that guaranteed women’s suffrage?",
          "answer": "Nineteenth Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "associate of Elizabeth Cady Stanton arrested for trying to vote in 1872?",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "first U.S. state to allow women to vote, nicknamed the “Equality State”?",
          "answer": "Wyoming"
        },
        {
          "question": "portion of the Educational Amendments of 1972 ensuring equal opportunities for the sexes?",
          "answer": "Title IX"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court case that established a right to privacy and shut down a contraceptives ban?",
          "answer": "Griswold v. Connecticut"
        },
        {
          "question": "former slave who invited blacks into the women’s movement with her “Ain’t I A Woman” speech?",
          "answer": "Sojourner Truth"
        },
        {
          "question": "women’s college that underwent a “non-merger merger” with Harvard in the 1970s?",
          "answer": "Radcliffe College"
        },
        {
          "question": "magazine started by journalist Gloria Steinem in 1971?",
          "answer": "Ms."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "DISCOURSES ON LIVY",
      "prompt": "Who or what was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the ancient Italian city whose history was chronicled by Livy?",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "medieval political scientist who wrote Discourses on Livy and The Prince?",
          "answer": "Niccol`o Macchiavelli"
        },
        {
          "question": "group of commoners who contrasted with patricians?",
          "answer": "plebs"
        },
        {
          "question": "leaderless form of government that author claimed was the natural consequence of democracy?",
          "answer": "anarchy"
        },
        {
          "question": "process by which the Five Good Emperors took the throne, exemplified by Trajan to Hadrian?",
          "answer": "adoption"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman general who defeated Hannibal at the Battle of Zama?",
          "answer": "Publius Cornelius Scipio Africanus"
        },
        {
          "question": "lawgiver of Sparta praised by that author?",
          "answer": "Lycurgus"
        },
        {
          "question": "second king of Rome praised for bringing it religion?",
          "answer": "Numa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BENGAL",
      "prompt": "In the history of Bengal, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "world’s second most populous country home to the state of West Bengal?",
          "answer": "Republic of India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim nation of which Bangladesh was the “East” portion until 1971?",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "large city of eastern India and capital of West Bengal?",
          "answer": [
            "Calcutta",
            "Kolkata"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Bengali Nobel laureate in literature who wrote the Indian and Bangladeshi national anthems?",
          "answer": "Rabindranath Tagore"
        },
        {
          "question": "disaster that caused three million deaths in 1943, studied by economist Amartya Sen?",
          "answer": "famine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian prime minister in 1971 who supported the independence of Bangladesh?",
          "answer": "Indira Ghandi"
        },
        {
          "question": "second largest Bangladeshi city whose armory was raided in 1930 by independence seekers?",
          "answer": "Chittagong"
        },
        {
          "question": "Maoist insurgency group targeted by Operation Steeplechase in the early 1970s?",
          "answer": [
            "Naxalite",
            "Naxalbari"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Shortly before his death, an opponent of this policy was shackled naked to the back of a Land Rover during an 1100 kilometer road trip. A campaign of “rolling mass action” against this policy led to the Bisho massacre, carried out by the armed forces of the Ciskei (20 pts)",
        "Bantustan. The armed group Umkhonto We Sizwe was established to fight this policy after the Sharpeville Massacre. This policy ended after the National Party was defeated in a 1994 election. (10 pts)",
        "Desmond Tutu and Nelson Mandela opposed, for ten points, what policy that denied black people rights in South Africa?"
      ],
      "answer": "apartheid"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this event, an executioner named Ser Nuto was lynched, hung by his foot, and ripped apart by a mob. A group called the Eight took power during this event, after which the (20 pts)",
        "Albizzi family rose to prominence. The first leader of this event was declared gonfaloniere of justice and was named Michele di Lando, and this event was partly caused by popular resentment over the power held by the (10 pts)",
        "Arte della Lana. The participants in this uprising were part of the popolo minuto and had little power since they were not part of a guild. For ten points, name this uprising of wool carders in Florence."
      ],
      "answer": "Revolt of the Ciompi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A folding screen and a large vase stand in the background of a Gustave Leonard de Jonghe painting of one of these people reclining, titled The Afternoon Siesta. A mandolin player with her back to the viewer was modeled off the artist’s previous painting The (20 pts)",
        "Valpin¸con Bather in a circular painting depicting dozens of these people. In an 1814 painting, one of these people carries a peacock-feather fan and has several (10 pts)",
        "additional vertebrae. For ten points, name these female harem slaves in the service of the sultan, of which Jean-Dominique Ingres [ANG] painted a “Grande” type."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "odalisque",
        "odalik",
        "A Reclining Odalisque",
        "La Grande Odalisque"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The most famous of these specific performances was supported by newcomers Billy Cox and Larry Lee. An early surviving recording of these performances took place at Merriweather Post Pavilion and, like the most famous of these events, includes the melody from (20 pts)",
        "“Taps.” The last of these performances came in Hawaii a month before the performer’s 1970 death in a London apartment. The most famous of these performances enjoys a good quality video recording due to the early (10 pts)",
        "morning light, as it came at the end of the Woodstock festival. For ten points, name these patriotic guitar performances by the leader of the Experience. ANSWER:JimiHendrixplayingtheStar Spangled Banner(orequivalents;promptonpartialanswers) (5) The Wood Green plot was a terrorist attempt to attack the London Underground using this substance. In 2013, this substance was included in letters that read “Maybe I have your attention now even if that means someone must die” and “I am (+) KC and I approve this message”; those letters were later traced to former actress Shannon Richardson. A platinum-iridium pellet containing this substance was shot out of an umbrella gun to assassinate (*) Bulgarian dissident Georgi Markov. For ten points, name this toxin derived from the castor oil plant that was put in letters addressed to Barack Obama in April 2013."
      ],
      "answer": "ricin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The winning commander in this battle had been called out of retirement to fight by Candarli Halil. The idea that it was lawful to break treaties with heretics helped Julian Cesarini convince one side to fight this battle. Ladislaus the (20 pts)",
        "Posthumous ascended to the throne following this battle that was preceded by the violation of the Peace of (10 pts)",
        "Szeged, and Wladyslaw III of Poland was killed in this battle. This battle was the culmination of the Long Campaign. For ten points, name this battle between Janos [yan-osh] Hunyadi’s Hungarians and Murad II near the Black Sea in 1444."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Varna"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This proposal called for the ban on “personal liberty laws,” which were used to circumvent the Fugitive Slave Act. A controversial part of this proposal banned Congress from later (20 pts)",
        "amending its terms. Another part of this proposal sought to reverse the Nebraska-Kansas Act and guarantee the ban of slavery above the (10 pts)",
        "36-30 line. Abraham Lincoln was the main force behind the rejection of, for ten points, what last attempt at a compromise before slave states seceded from the Union, proposed by a Kentuckian member of the Know Nothing Party?"
      ],
      "answer": "Crittenden Compromise"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author called attention to the wrongs of the Bangladesh Liberation War in his poem “September on Jessore Road.” He claimed “Strange now to think of you, gone without corsets and eyes” in an elegy for his mother Naomi. This author of (20 pts)",
        "“Kaddish” also placed Federico Garcia Lorca and Walt Whitman in a “Supermarket in California.” He repeatedly assured Carl Solomon that “I’m (10 pts)",
        "with you in Rockland” in a poem that was the subject of a notable 1957 obscenity trial. For ten points, name this Beat poet who lamented “I saw the best minds of my generation destroyed by madness” in his poem “Howl.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Irwin Allen Ginsberg"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One plank of this proposal would have prevented teenage mothers from receiving welfare. This plan for the 104th Congress was developed by a Georgia representative whose Presidential campaign in (20 pts)",
        "2012 included a scandal regarding a six-figure Tiffany bill. This proposal included the “Taking Back Our Streets” Act and the aforementioned “Personal Responsibility” Act, which was vetoed by President (10 pts)",
        "Clinton. For ten points, give this three-word name of the 1994 agenda offered by Newt Gingrich in a successful midterm campaign to gain Republican control of Congress."
      ],
      "answer": "Contract With America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An attempt to enforce this law resulted in the building of a 2000-mile-long hedge to curb smuggling from one coast to the other called the Inland Customs Line. Archibald Rowlands attempted to repeal this law, but was prevented from doing so by Archibald (20 pts)",
        "Wavell. This law affected people living in the Orissa state who had to purchase the namesake substance instead of collecting it themselves. The most famous (10 pts)",
        "resistance to this law led to the Second Round Table Conference with Lord Irwin and ended at a beach in Dandi. For ten points, name this unpopular law in British India that taxed a substance collected from the sea."
      ],
      "answer": "British salt tax in India"
    }
  ]
}